<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Lord Lieutenant General of Ireland.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1641-1649 : Ormonde)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O441A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214477</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826643</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826643</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31048</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53434)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31048)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1766:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Lord Lieutenant General of Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Lord Lieutenant (1641-1649 : Ormonde)</author>
                  <author>Ormonde, James Butler, Duke of, 1610-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Corck :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare 1648. and are to be sold at Roches building.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31048:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE LORD LIEVTENANT GENERALL OF IRELAND.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at Corck, in the yeare 1648. and are to be ſold at Roches building.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:31048:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:31048:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
            <head>BY THE LORD LIEVTENANT GENERALL OF IRELAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>ORMOND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O prevent the too frequent prejudices incident through jealouſies, diſtruſts, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtructions to all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, Wee accompt it not the leaſt worthy our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour upon the inſtant of our Arrivall to prepare this people, whoſe welfare Wee contend for, with a right underſtanding of thoſe intentions in Us, which in Order to his Maieſties ſervice Wee deſire may terminate in their good.</p>
            <p>To enumerate the ſeverall reaſons by which Wee were induced (for preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Engliſh intereſt) to leave the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and other his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Garriſons then under our power in this Kingdome, in the hands of thoſe intruſted by his two Houſes of Parliament, were to ſet forth a
<pb facs="tcp:31048:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
Narative in place of a manifeſt. It may ſuffice to be knowne, that thoſe Tranſactions had for one mayne ground this Confidence. That by being under the power of the Houſes they would upon a happy expected Compoſure of Affaires in England revert unto, and be reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in his Maieſtie as his proper right.</p>
            <p>But having found how contrary to the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the well affected to his Maieſties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration in England, the Power of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath unhappily devolved to hands im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed onely in the Art and labour of pulling downe and ſubverting the Fundamentalls of Monarchy (with whom a pernicious Partie in this Kingdome doe equally Sympathize &amp; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operate.) And being filled with a deepe ſence of the dutie and obligations that are upon Us ſtrictly to imbrace all oportunities of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our endeavours towards the recovery of his Maieſties iuſt rights in any part of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Having obſerved the Proteſtant Army in the Province of Mounſter (by ſpeciall providence diſcovering the Arts and practizes uſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle the members thereof, in ingagements as directly contrary to their duties towards God &amp; man, as to their intentions and reſolutions) to have found meanes to manifeſt the Candor &amp; Integrity thereof in a diſclaimer of any obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to, or concurrence with thoſe powers or perſons which have ſo groſely varyed even their
<pb facs="tcp:31048:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
owne profeſſed principles of preſerving his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Perſon and rights, by confining him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a moſt ſtrict Impriſonment, his Maieſtie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vouchſafing graciouſly to accept the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſaid Army as an eminent and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable expreſſion of their fidelity toward him, and in teſtimony thereof having layd his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands upon us to make our repayre unto this Province to diſcharge the duties of our place.</p>
            <p>Wee have as well in obedience thereunto as in purſuance of our owne duty and deſire to advance his Maieſties ſervice, reſolved to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence our approbation and eſteeme of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the ſaid Army by publiſhing unto the world our like determination in the ſame enſueing particulers. And accordingly Wee profeſſe and declare.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to improve our utmoſt endeavours for the ſettlement of the Proteſtant Religion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of the beſt Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to defend the King in his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to maintaine the Priviledges and Freedome of Parliament, and the Libertie of the Subiects; That in Order hereunto Wee ſhall oppoſe to the hazard of our lives, thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells of this Kingdome who ſhall refuſe their Obedience to his Maieſtie, upon ſuch Termes as Hee hath thought fit by us to require it; And
<pb facs="tcp:31048:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
Wee ſhall endeavour to the utmoſt, the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of that <hi>Jndependent-Party,</hi> who have thus fiercely laboured the extirpation of the true Proteſtant Religion; The ruine of our Prince; The diſhonour of Parliament, and the Vaſſaladge of our Fellow Subiects, againſt all thoſe who ſhall depend upon them, or adhere unto them; And that this our undertaking might not appeare obnoxious to the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> but that Wee deſire a firme union and Agreement be preſerved betwixt us; Wee doe likewiſe declare, that Wee will continue free trafique, and Comerce with all his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties good Subiects of <hi>England;</hi> And that Wee will not in the leaſt manner preiudice any of them that ſhall have recourſe to our Harbours, either in their bodyes, ſhipps, or goods, nor ſhall Wee take any thing from them without payment of ready money for the ſame; And now that by his Maieſties ſaid Command, Wee have proceeded to reenter upon the worke of his ſervice in this Province, Wee conceive no higher Teſtimonie can be given of his Maieſties acceptation, or of the eſtimation Wee beare about Us towards their Proceedings then by reſorting unto them in perſon with His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Authority, and exhibiting unto them the incouragement and ſatisfaction they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in this aſſurance. That as Wee beare an eſpeciall regard to their preſent undertakings
<pb facs="tcp:31048:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
and performances accompanyed with a reall. Sence of their former ſufferings. So leaſt there ſhould any advantage be derived unto thoſe who indeavour to improve all oportunities of ſowing ſedition and diſtruſt by this ſuggeſtion, that the former differences in Iudgement and opinion which have induced perſons to ſerve diverſly under His Majeſty, and the Parliament, will occaſion prejudice, or ill reſentments to ariſe towards ſuch Perſons as have not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly concurred in Iudgement with others in His Maieſties ſervice, Wee doe declare, that Wee are quallified with ſpeciall power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from His Majeſtie, to aſſure them, that no diſtinction ſhall be made in any ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, but that all perſons now intereſted and engaged in this Cauſe, ſhall be reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with equall fervour and regard; And that Wee ſhall make it our endeavours ſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and confirme His Majeſties Gracious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure towards them, as that Wee will never call to memorie any paſt difference in opinion, Judgement, Action, or Profeſſion to the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of any Member of this Army, or any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon relating to it, but on the contrary, ſhall be very ready to atteſt our good affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in the diſcharge of ſuch good Offices as ſhall be in our power, In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne whereof Wee ſhall onely expect their perſeverance in their preſent ingagements for
<pb facs="tcp:31048:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
his Maieſties ſervice with ſuch allacrity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and affection, as may ſuit with their late publique declaration, &amp; Profeſſions. To whom Wee deſire this aſſurance alſo may be inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. That as Wee ſhall in the future uſe our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt care &amp; diligence to provide for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from the like hardſhips, to thoſe they have formerly undergone; So Wee have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready imployed our beſt induſtry and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for the ſettlement of ſuch a courſe, as we may (with moſt reaſon) hope will in theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine times produce a conſtant &amp; competent Subſiſtance for them, enabling them to make ſuch a progreſſe in their preſent undertakings as may with the accompliſhment of the great ends thereof eſtabliſh their owne honour and content. Thus much Wee have thought fit to publiſh unto the world, to furniſh it with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of ſtrong conviction againſt Us, if We ever ſwerve (to the beſt of our power from the iuſt wayes of maintaining the true Proteſtant Religion, the honour and intereſt of His Sacred Maieſtie, the iuſt rights of Parliament, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subiects, and the ſafety, quiet &amp; welfare of the people intruſted to our Care.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>6. Octob. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31048:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
